okay we'll
meditate watch your
breath
e e
come to that room with the golden
sunlight
pouring e
see the little Sky out the
window the upper half
of e
see the mountains across the valley
see your teacher sitting in front of
you look at their face
into their
eyes feel the love stay there happy
contented that's enough for the next
five minutes you don't need to go
anywhere else you have nothing else to
do
e
e e
come back to this
room then slowly open your
eyes okay
so we
were we were at 11 I think we finished
the the objects of the senses which
might distract your
mind and we're on our way to achieving
uh at
13 is called uh L say
l
l uh lamba means
uh a patch like if you if you sew a pat
if you ripped your coat and you sew a
patch on it that's a lent and L jopa
means
uh you have constant continuity on the
object but there are patches where you
don't have where you're not on the
object okay so most of the time you're
on the object and then there are patches
where you're not on the object so the
the name is a little bit what do you
call it deceptive you know patch-like
meditation would seem to mean meditation
which comes in patches so some people
have misunderstood the name what it
means is the patch is the time of the
object Okay so most of the time your
hold coat you're on the object and then
there's a little Parts where you're not
on the object
okay so you go from Sam fly on the fly
on the cowpie to
G where you have some continuity but
mostly off the object and then L the J
which means you're almost always on the
object and then there are spots where
you're not on the object okay so the
name is is deceptive call it patch like
uh
uh that's 13 actually 13 yeah Lage Jer
is
13 11 was the sense
object
uh
12 12 says G say
TBE to TBE top means uh the power of
pulling the Mind back to the object
literally Juma means
to or to remember something but it means
to bring the to bring the Mind back to
the
object so that's the power which is
active during the third state of mind
which is where you're rarely off the
object okay only patches off the object
okay and then Juma draws you back so
Juma is getting strong by the time you
get
to
level three J is getting stronger it
pulls you back quickly and you're more
on the object than you're off the object
okay at levels one and two you
were more off than on the level three
you're more on than
off I I would I I believe this is where
most of us spend our time between level
one and level three okay I mean if
you're honest I spend most of my time
between one and three probably so the
the goal of this chart the reason to go
through this chart is that you get some
Benchmark of where you are you have to
go to level N9 plus to see emptiness
directly and most of us are hanging out
around two or three okay I think three
is a good day for me two is a typical
day one when I didn't get any sleep
something like that okay so we most
they're hanging out around 1 two and
three okay three if you're lucky right
uh then number 14 says
CH uh 14 means
means subtle dullness
okay and this is the most important
thing you can talk about in
meditation okay of all the things you
can talk about subtle dullness is the
most important thing okay why why is it
important to talk about subtle
dullness uh you have meta you're on the
object you have
uh your mind is fairly
fresh but you don't
have say
say n g a r uh don't move your tongue
just just close your
throat yeah uh L means uh
intensity okay
intensity it's a word in tibetan which
is used to describe also normally it's
used to describe the temper on a piece
of Steel on a blade a steel The
Temper so if you temper a blade it's
difficult to uh dull it okay I I I don't
know what you do exactly I think you you
heat it and then you cool it again and
you heat it and cool again you might
layer
it uh you might uh like cut toffee you
might layer it and then uh it gets Nar
so Nar is uh intensity of the steel and
added hardness of the steel okay in
meditation you you got to get a feeling
for what is and if you do then I then I
think we did a good job this week okay
so we have to talk about what's Nar Nar
means what's intensity really
mean
uh so dull gross dullness you you lose
the object and you're almost falling
asleep you can uh what do you call
it bring on a state of gold Stillness
consciously what's the word for that you
can
replicate gross dullness consciously you
can consciously create a state of gross
dullness if you want to see what it's
like just eat a lot of heavy food and
then try to meditate right after that
okay then you can experience gross
dullness I mean sometimes it's useful to
do that kind of thing you know just eat
a big meal and then try to meditate and
see how bad it is okay uh or you could
stay up too late and then try to
meditate and then you just you cannot
okay like I was I remember I was in one
particularly deep
meditation and I kept hitting a block
you know I kept hitting this what do you
call upper limit thing and I couldn't
get past it and I was like I was
examining my whole mind you I was like
going to this corner of the mind and
that corner of the mind and I'm like
where's this subtle block you know and
then suddenly I had this this big
realization came in my mind you didn't
get enough sleep last night and no
matter what you do you're not going to
go past this limit you you can't if you
didn't have enough sleep the night
before you can't okay so so there's two
things you can do right away to stop
dness don't eat too much especially
before you meditate
and you got to make decisions right I
mean you look at a plate of
food and and that's a choice you have a
choice am I going to meditate well in
the next three hours or not and
sometimes you choose the food you
sometimes you say oh what the heck you
know I'm just G to have a big meal and
I'll be Min you know like but you got to
at least what do you call it in a
football
game you what do you call it you what do
you call when you surrender a goal or
something you there's a word for
it you surrender the first 10 yards so
that they don't throw a long
pass what do they call
it I don't know like like there's three
minutes left in the game it's third down
you surrender the first 10 15 yards
because it doesn't matter if they can
make a short
pass you're just trying to catch the
Long pass
you you there's a word in
English
anyway guys obviously are football
player there's some word for it but
anyway when you're looking at the food
and you can surrender the next three
hours you could say okay I'm not going
to see emptiness in the next three hours
and then eat it you know and that's a
decision that you make you know you say
eating is more important for me right
now than than Poss possibly seeing
emptiness I mean I don't want to put a
guil trip on
you uh but that's always the choice you
know you look at a big plate of food
it's too much food and it's going to
conqu you out
and and then you make a call and you
decide you know you can live off
comfortably off of about a quarter of
what they put on an American plate of
food you know it's it's just a choice
you know you can live comfortably eat a
quarter stop you won't feel hungry till
the next meal it's okay you know the
rest is just what do you call it
desire
so uh just see try you make a decision
you make a call then sleeping you know
it's your
responsibility as a yogi to sleep in
them okay if you want to help other
people if you want to serve the
world uh you have to get as sleep okay
and that's all and you have to figure
out what it is you need and it and it's
like for me it's 8 hours it's 7 hours
and you can
sometimes consciously get left because
you have some important spiritual thing
to do but know that you are risking a
lot more you know like you you won't be
good the next day you'll be cranky
you'll you collect a lot of Bad Karma
you won't be able to meditate you are
what do they call that
huh is that the sacrifice plan it's not
a
sacrifice you are surrendering or
something no it's like you give up that
area of the playing field because it's
not important anymore okay uh so anyway
you are uh you're giving up
okay anyway uh it's probably in the text
somewhere uh so
you you you can decide not to get enough
sleep if it's a conscious decision you
know I have a virtuous activity I have
to build some C tomorrow's the 30th you
know I'm going to stay up all night
there there's times when that's
appropriate you know but mostly it's not
appropriate okay even for a virtuous
thing because because you're forfeiting
whatever it's called
you're surrendering the next day's
virtue you will be cranky you will be
useless you won't be able to meditate
you won't have a good practice you might
break your practice you might break the
habit of practice generally it's a bad
idea to break it for anything okay
generally it's a bad idea
to Forfeit surrender your practice for
anything because it just doesn't it's
illogical to you know you you give one
night and then you there two day or
something like that and it's it's
generally not a good idea okay if you
don't get enough sleep you cannot avoid
D it's not possible okay that's all you
are forfeiting the next couple
days hang there's
some so word anyway
okay I'll think about it
uh so that's grow G donus and that's not
such a difficult thing to recognize
right I had I had a cool gross donus on
Sixth Street once in New York we had a
little Temple there and uh I fell asleep
meditating and I fell over and I hit my
head on a closet door and that's gross
donut okay I had this big bump on my
head okay that's gross
donut but subtle dullness is is very
very important and if you don't learn
anything else this week you should learn
what subtle dullness is subtle dullness
is you are not turned on by The
Meditation you're not feeling turned on
by the
med people like you and me do CH r
ray
uh we don't even have uh we are we are
rarely turned on by meditation
anyway okay but
but a sign that you have subtle dullness
subtle dullness should be object that
we're talking about this week okay at
least I'm talking you don't get to talk
uh and it's that you're not turned on
you're in meditation you're on the
object the mind is fairly fresh and
you're not excited and you're not in
grow you're not having a fine time okay
and you got to learn to distinguish
between those two states of mind okay a
good meditation and a great
meditation because a good meditation is
where you have subtle domas okay I don't
know if you'd call it good actually but
uh you're not turned on all right
sometimes it's because the object
doesn't turn you on so you should find
an object that turns you on so again
selection of your meditation object is
crucial okay if it's not an object which
excites you then find some other object
okay uh all right and and then you will
you can find one personally it's for me
it's my teacher but uh it could be I
don't know what it could be emptiness
medit a or whatever for you okay but
find your job is to find a meditation
object that interests you so much that
you will daydream about it and that you
will feel passionate about it okay and
if you don't have anything like that
you'll never have none okay so you have
to find an object which
is which is extremely what do you call
it Pleasant okay for you and meaningful
for you and you enjoy you enjoy D
dreaming about that thing
real Nar feels
like being on the edge of your seat in a
Harry Potter movie okay and you're like
oh my God you know what's going to
happen next you know and people are
offering your popcorn and you're like
you're like you don't even eat the
popcorn which means it's the it's a
really good part of the movie you know
you're like you you know or you're in a
you're reading a book and and someone
calls your name and you don't hear them
okay uh that that's that's more somebody
says dinner's ready and you hear
something but it doesn't what do you
call register that's n okay or for me if
I'm listening to certain kinds of music
like good music like Jimmy Hendricks or
neon because they haven't written good
music since then but
uh but it I just engrossed in it or what
do you call it lost in it and that's not
okay
so don't be satisfied with less than
that if your meditation is less than
that you're not going to keep it up you
will quit after a while okay you'll get
tired of it if it's not really exciting
to you if you don't feel passionate
about it if it's not like totally sexy
to you then choose another object okay
because if you don't you'll just quit
after a while you you'll get tired of it
you'll do it because you feel obligated
to and that's AOW POS reason to meditate
okay it should be like you can't help
yourself you know like nobody told you
to uh what do you call
it nobody has to tell you coffee tastes
good you know nobody has to sit there
and try to convince you that coffee
tastes good you know you want coffee or
chocolate or whatever it is you know
nobody's like shaking you Nick you know
you got to eat chocolate it tastes
really good you know like you just want
it you know CU it does taste good or or
you're addicted to coffee and you got to
have a coffee you know and the if the
meditation is not like that you won't
keep it up you'll quit sooner or later
you'll just fizzle out okay so find an
object which is which turns you
on okay and then and then you'll have
and you got to get toar or you're not
you just never be a good meditator it's
got to
be engrossed in this thing turned on by
the things that's Nar okay if you don't
have that and you're just hanging out on
the object that's subtle
dullness uh the threeyear retrea a
couple days ago was it they asked me uh
give us final advice you know what the
final advice K gave me it was uh keep
your mind in the Y you know we went up
and we we had a three-hour time slot you
know and we went up said k p know what's
your final word he said keep your mind
in the YT and and then we said okay what
else and he said that's it go to go way
you know and uh uh so I didn't do so
good but
uh they asked me what advice what's your
final advice I said watch subtle
dullness because you can spend a
thousand days meditating in subtle
dullness and you don't get anywhere you
won't get anywhere and then Pabon has a
very beautiful section very very
beautiful section that I think you might
want to think about he says
if you're having trouble detecting
subtle dness during your meditation
which shouldn't be so hard okay are you
turned on or not if you're not turned on
you have solid dness okay if you're not
like totally turned on by this
object so that if someone you shouldn't
be looking at the clock for when is it
going to ring you should be worrying
about the ring is going to disturb your
this sexy meditation you're having you
got the difference
right so in the meditation the the the
Judgment call of whether you're having
subtle dullness or not is are you turned
on during the meditation okay but what P
says something very interesting and I
think it might be really helpful for all
of us okay uh I propose it as one of the
most useful meditation advises I ever
gotten he says after you come out of the
meditation examine your behavior for one
or two hours are you Spacey
are you spacy you know and I was most of
the street of retreat you know you you
get out of meditation and you're like
moving around the Y
like you know and you're like uh what
was I going to do next it's like a you
feel kind of forgetful or something and
I I like to call it absentminded
Professor you're like like what was I I
was going to uh what was I supposed to
be next after this meditation you know
or you feel just sort of out of it it it
could be a pleasant feeling okay it's
kind of like you're stoned or something
and and you're just like wow you know
and then the opposite of that the other
extreme is uh what do you call it gross
agitation and that's where you you the
alarm goes off you open your eyes and
you say I got to email Joe you know and
all your meditation partners are going
yeah so what were you meditating about
you know the this the the two seconds
after the alarm ring they're like I got
to email Joe they get they get they
actually get up and say I got to email
Joe and you're like yeah well I know
what you are meditating about okay so
that's if you are moving fast out of the
meditation observe your behavior for 10
minutes out of the meditation if you're
moving fast if you're doing several
tasks it's that you line them up during
the
meditation
okay okay so you can objectively judge
the state of your meditation period
after in the 10 minutes afterwards and
see how if you're jumping up and doing
four different things quickly it's
because you were meditating on them and
then you had agitation and you were off
on planning is agitation right because
it's things you want to do uh so those
are two tests for the two extremes
subtle dullness
if you feel somewhat out of it or spaced
out or stoned when you come out of the
meditation and you see that's dangerous
because some people think that's
calmness they say the meditation works
because I'm I'm calm but they're really
just spaced out so try to distinguish
the difference between calm and spaced
out spaced out is not calm how do you
know call the person stupid during the
space out period and they react
immediately the mind is not come the
mind is space out they'll get angry
they'll they'll respond quickly they'll
react
quickly space out is an unstable state
of mind and an unhealthy State of Mind
calm real calm you know is
different uh so that's not try to
distinguish between calm and space do
smoking a dope or taking some wine and
then feeling Buzz or peaceful is not
peaceful it's a bad habit and and the
mind gets weaker
and uh and then it takes more wine to
get to that place and then you have to
do it two times a day and then you have
to do it three times a day and you can't
that's not peace that's baced out right
different it's different that's Stone
right so then
uh what does it feel like if you come
out of a good meditation okay like you
can you can try to judge the quality of
your meditation from how you act in the
in the minutes 10 minutes after 10
minutes after you get up slowly you get
up
calmly you you you're sharp you're
focused you have tasks to do you
prioritize them carefully and you move
through them effectively and
successfully and clearly you know and
even if it's like you're going to cook
dinner for somebody you go get up out of
your meditation your mind comes to the
dinner then it wasn't it wasn't on the
dinner during the meditation you get up
out of meditation your mind is calm
clear you think about what you have to
do today after the meditation and then
you think I have to cook someone a meal
today and then you're like I'm going to
need you open the fridge you know I need
potato I need this I need that and
you're just clear and all your movements
are what do you call it economical and
efficient and well considered and well
prioritized and your mind is clear and
your mind is healthy and strong and
that's how you'll know you'll be a very
effective person and you'll be a very
successful person and you feel calm
while you're doing you know you're
preparing dinner and you know the
water's going off and the potatoes are
boiling and you're supposed to be
mashing the the chilies and and you're
moving you're dancing through the
kitchen and and you're like calm and
you're you're into it you know and and
you're effective and that means you had
a good meditation so if you get out of
meditation you're like you know
what was I supposed to do today you know
and that means you had subtle dumbness
I'm just trying to get you into this
mood of Judge the quality of meditation
by by the quality of your State of Mind
in the in the hour or so immediately
following the meditation okay then you
can retroactively decide whether you had
subtle DRS if you can't detect it during
okay so check that out even here okay
even here how do you feel when you get
up do you feel a little spacey after
meditation or or do you feel a little
sharper or do you feel nervous and you
have to do three things because that
means you had agitation okay all
right describes lende joa okay here so
sorry so 14 was subtle dness okay and
that's a uh there's a rabbit
now on the on the elephant's back you
see him at 14 he's added a rabbit he
doesn't say it in the text but I guess
that's subtle bonus okay because the
elephant
was GR
and the elephant's head is already
mostly white okay meaning the grow dness
is is going
away starting to lose your gross
dullness but you've got dullness left
and that's now subtle dullness okay and
he's I think he's depicted it as a as a
rabbit let's see if he says anything
more
uh then we'll go to 15
[Music]
the monkey looking back repres we're on
15 the monkey looking back repres
presents the ability to tell when your
mind is wandering and to refocus it upon
the object of
meditation which brings you
to number
16 which is
n uh level number four okay it's a
little hot you think no do you feel
hot
okay not a good one to
say again what was number 15 uh 15 is
near
J sorry no 15 was and what it means is
you are reaching a very sophisticated
ability to bring your mind back
the and it is so the recollection the
recollective ability the TBA is so well
developed by now that that you can never
again from here on lose the object
completely you will never be completely
off the object again after level four
and I dare say in my own case I rarely
get to level
four I can't say that I spend the whole
five minutes or 10 minutes without
thinking of anything else because that's
what Naro Joko would be okay so that's a
little
scary like you don't get to level four
it's difficult to get to level
four you cannot during level four you
can't lose the object completely anymore
but says you can have very strong chinga
Anda meaning what dullness and agitation
okay you're you're you cannot lose the
object but the quality of the meditation
is
bad okay you you can't lose the object
completely but you're still subject to
severe attack of thinking about lunge
under the
object and uh what's the other one oh
getting
sleepy all right but still holding on to
the object Weekly right got it you don't
lose the object but the quality is not
very
good these
two levels patchlike meditation which
should be called patchlike
distraction right
be better right and then uh what we call
n jopa maintaining the Mind tightly on
the object these two are achieved to the
power of
Juma which means that was
the that was what was in the Monk's left
hand the chain right these two are
achieved to the ability to pull the
object
back to hold the object
back so let's meditate some more
what I want to do generally
strategically here is uh you're going to
learn all line levels all six Powers all
four states of mind all five problems
all eight
idot and then we're going to try to
identify them during our meditation
because that's the big deal first you
learn them and then you identify them
during your
meditation watch your bread
just before you go into the breath you
might check the condition of your
forehead the corners of your
mouth and the tops of your
eyelids and that's where tension
manifests if you can consciously release
the tops of your
eyelids your
forehead and the corners of your mouth
if you can consciously release any
tension there it will help you meditate
then go to your
breath e
come to the golden
room
relax feel peace of mind to be in the
that room let that room evoke in you
feelings of peace and contentment e
look at the Blue
Sky the radiance of the golden light and
the radiance of the blue
sky are traditional methods of
preventing subtle dullness
look across the valley to the mountains
looking at a a wide landscape a spacious
landscape is also a traditional method
of loosening an overly tight
Focus e
and invite your Lama ask your Lama if
they would Grace you with their presence
I would like you to take as your
meditation object the feeling of
presence the feeling that they are
present in the room just
that
e e
stay on their presence
now I would like to ask you to try to
stay especially aware of what kind of
problems are close to happening in your
meditation or already happened did you
think about
dinner or are you feeling
sleepy is your cold bothering you uh I'm
going to ask people after the meditation
to to tell us what what are the
what kind of problem was coming up for
you uh that affected the quality of your
meditation so go back to the presence of
your
teacher and then try to observe when you
when you come off and and what's what's
your most typical problem
it might be lack of being turned on lack
of
none
e
e e
examine what distractions you've had
examine if you've had any loss of
freshness of the
Mind examine if you feel turned on by
the object
see if you can bring up a sense of
contentment with
the with sitting in the room with your
teacher or a sense of relief or
comfort that you could actually feed off
of and that's t z say that's
concentrate
to
sustenance a feeling of well-being
and then in a sense of wellbeing come
back to this
one and then slowly open your eyes
uh there was a thing in ballet like I
worked on ballet for a while and uh one
of my teachers would say I had trouble
with P right in a certain direction and
then they would say observe if you fall
to the right or to the left and then uh
that I did and it it was always to the
right and then they'd say
observe which in the compass is it to
the west to you know what's the degree
of the Fall what's the axis of the fall
and then and then I found out it was
interesting because it was always the
same direction and it was always in the
same place so then they said well just
put a little
counterweight the other way and then
everything was fine you see so I think
what you'll find in your meditation is
similar the the problem you have will
will be typical to you and you'll keep
having the same kind of problem so try
to Mark the fall you know where which
way does the Mind fall out does it fall
out to thinking about dinner or does it
fall out to feeling sleepy or do you not
feel like do you not feel very excited
about the meditation you see what I mean
then you'll you'll learn what's your
typical problem is and then you can you
can counterbalance a little bit to the
opposite way okay like get more
asleep or worry less about dinner or you
know or try to pick an object which is a
little bit more compelling for you okay
so I'd like to ask if anybody has any
typical problem that they caught
themselves like typical
F yeah
Peter I
a uh he said the meditation just doing
meditation in
general oh so it distracts you yeah the
Mind goes for
that I'm going to take the opportunity
to bring up a to totally different thing
and then I'll come back to your promise
okay uh no I
mean I was thinking about it and I
thought I want to say it while we're
still talk while you're still talking
we had
sh we had five qualities of the place of
meditation that we talked about this
morning they
were uh easy to get honest
supplies uh the place has been blessed
preferably by some but great meditator
the place is healthy and not
dangerous what's the other
one good friends good companions to
meditate with by the way they could be
in the same room or in a different room
or in the same cabin or a different
cabin but you're in retreat with
somebody or you're doing your med daily
meditation with someone who's
hardcore and they you draw strength from
them and then what was the last one good
training you know what you know what the
hell you're doing okay now you're
started getting a sense of how deep this
training is you know and we're just
barely
started so I don't want you to conf
those are five qualities of what we call
TBE T tumba TBE means a conducive place
for meditation and that was the first of
six different so I don't want to confuse
the five and the six
okay the a conducive place for
meditation had five different qualities
which we already talked about but there
are five
other
uh prerequisites for a good meditation
practice that we didn't talk about yet
in this Retreat what what
what the first one was those five then
it was which means
what don't want a lot of stuff okay
don't like be thinking
about I need better food or I didn't get
exactly the kind of oil on the food that
I wanted or you know it was a little too
hot or a little too cold or the cooks
are always putting to my salt or you
know my place isn't as comfortable as
someone else's place it's a it's a
mental
complaining about the state of
your your life and it's just a habit
it's just a bad habit other people are
going through much worse things and
they're
happy and they're not in the habit of
complaining about it okay so that's
that's then cha what's
cha see yeah what ever you do get you
feel a deep sense of enjoyment of it
okay you know somebody cooked me a
veggie burger today you know and
somebody drove it from the store and
somebody made it in some Factory you
know with their hands with their life
which used up an hour of their life
there's a whole chain of people who have
sacrificed hours of their life to get
this veggie burger here for me so it's a
little undercooked which are you gonna
think about you know that it's a little
undercooked or that 20 people have
sacrificed Irreplaceable hours of their
life to get that veggie burger in front
of you you don't it's just a choice
right both are true it is undercooked
but it also used up 20 hours of human
people's lives that are irreplaceable to
them so what should you think about you
could think about either one you could
be constantly un happy with what you
have or you could be constantly happy
with all the work that people did to
give it to you okay and and that's
better for meditation okay the second
state of mind is better for meditation
so CH
sorry then what was the next
one uh give up busy mind busy mind don't
be too busy don't take on too much stuff
don't have too much stuff on your plate
it hurts your
meditation have enough State stuff on
your plate to keep your mind fresh and
what do they call it stimulated in a
healthy way but don't overdo which makes
you scattered okay it's the difference
between s stimulated and Scattered learn
to draw the line between stimulated and
Scattered a person who's not doing
anything at all gets dull a person who's
doing a a good job at a li limited
number of tasks for them is stimulated
and then if you're overwhelmed with two
things or 23 things you should cut down
okay that's number four right what was
number
five no it's not because de and choke
shap are two separate
ones okay stay on a stay in a conducive
play uh don't want too much stuff be
happy what you have and enjoy it number
three number four was avoid busy don't
be overwhelmed okay don't try to do too
much stuff but number five is the most
important one and it's the answer to
Peter's question okay I'm getting there
all right this is gu your thing you
know uh keep your morality okay like
don't hurt other people basically don't
hurt other people that's all don't hurt
anybody okay be nice to
everybody and that's that's the most
important quality that's the most
important prerequisite for meditation
why did I bring it up in conjunction
with Peter's
nose every distraction you ever have in
meditation is a ripening of a past Karma
period okay you want to stop all the
problems of your meditation that's it
you know it all goes back to how you're
treating other people if you if a if a
thought about lunch pops up in your mind
during your meditation it had a cause
and it was that you distracted somebody
else like you overworked somebody else
or you pressed somebody else they were
busy they were doing something you came
in un un interrupted them you know and
then you have the karma of interrupting
somebody who's trying to focus or
concentrate on something is coming back
to you as a distraction in your
meditation so that that right there is
the crucial thing you can't stop the the
interruption consciously we've been
talking about all these antidotes they
don't work they are aspirins they are
aspirins okay go to the source of the of
the interruption which is hurting other
people disturbing other people something
negative done to another person every
distraction you ever got all the
dullness that ever overwhelmed
you the lack of intensity the lack of n
what's what's a karma for a lack of n
no you haven't made other people's lives
like intensely interesting or intensely
pleasurable you know like you've you've
been satisfied to let the people around
you be or feel you don't try to make
them feel inspired or or deeply
interested or passionate or you know
it's okay with you if they're just dull
all day and you don't make any attempt
to brighten up up their life or make
their life more interesting or challenge
them or you know or Inspire
them or get them turned on and then and
then you're overcome by this lack of
being turned on okay turn on other
people you will be turned
on and it's fun right SOC consciously if
you want to have n you have to turn on
other people's lives make people's lives
interesting for
them okay do what what you can to
brighten up another person's day we went
by the gas truck guy he was putting his
chains on his truck we sat and talked
with him he seemed to have be happy that
someone was interested in him you know
and it was like a 10-second
interchange and then uh it was and then
you know and then you'll have some gar 3
days later in your meditation and you
don't know where it came from okay so so
number five so why why did I into that
you got to help somebody has a nose
problem you know like find somebody who
has some kind of pain and help them and
then that meditation obstacle will go go
away okay so I did get to his question
right but we might as well do number six
while we're
here which
was
huh yeah uh
yeah uh which
mean which means
what yeah R I would say random thoughts
the example that's given in scripture is
is D which has lots of meanings but I I
would almost take it
as you could take it as thoughts about
sex or something like you can read it
that way but it's not just sex it's just
random thoughts about stuff you want
or it's more like fixations or or what
do you call those obsessions like that
you know some people got to think about
cigarettes or some people got to think
about girls or some people got to think
about certain songs
or you know N means
uh useless thought useless random
thought that passes through your mind
regularly that's the definition
ofana in
Sanskrit
orpa useless random obsessive thoughts
which is normally sex or food uh okay or
fame say again
phoy uh you could say that also you
could say
uh the study of useless things or
something yeah distracting
Pursuits
okay okay who else had are we supposed
to
stop yeah technically we're supposed to
stop I want to hear can we do mine I
want to hear a few more people's typical
distractions isn't the answer to
everything to be the same the answer to
everything is the
same you're right no you're
right let's prove it
um my my attention starts strongly and T
was off the point where I start fall
asleep and and I'm still
not yeah I okay I'll give you a very
cool thing she said uh she starts out
with a strong attention and then it uh
degrades and then there's a until it
gets to almost
sleepy try to conceive of the gradual
degrading of your attention as the
attenuation of a karmic
seed okay so the seed broke open when
you started the meditation and then its
effects started to
dwindle and then it stopped like in the
way that a tree dies over the course of
30 40 years but it with you it's
happening in 3 minutes you see what I
mean no seriously because it's a thought
it's an it's an attention span the
reason attention spans
diminish is because of a karmic seed is
is wearing out in the moment you you're
watching a attention go like that and
there's a parallel lessening of the
power of the seed which opened over here
the seed opened at the beginning of the
meditation it gave its effect and by
giving its effect it died so that
natural with all composed things right
all produced things the Buddha said that
right so what would you do about
it
SE yeah you'd like to have other seeds
come off be there to to it'd be nice if
this if it a seed went off for attention
the attention started to degrade and
within a millisecond another seed went
off and kind of what do you call it
propped it up and seeds kept going up to
going off to prop it up you would have
to collect multiple seeds for attention
which again in my mind one one example
of that seed would be not interrupting
others who are trying to focus okay and
that could be at the store you know like
the the the teller is taking care of
somebody else and you want to know where
the popcorn is which shelf is the
popcorn on and this person is trying to
focus on the cash register and you're
like bugging them about popcorn and
there's somebody else waiting for them
and then then you you've Disturbed
someone else's
attention so think about
that maybe one more you
Nancy because of the magical quality of
the light all of a sudden I thought of
The Little Prince yeah yeah yeah and I
was like was off the yeah good you have
little prince movie going on uh so she
said because the light was so magical
then she started to think of little
prince I started to think of
tree and gifts under the tree and then
the last gift I opened and then it was
pretty cool
and so I want to raise one more
suggestion for
meditation when you get good at
meditating and you get to a certain
stage of
meditation it becomes in a very
productive pursuit to trace back a
distraction to its source so so I'm on
opening my Christmas gift why cuz I was
thinking of gifts under the tree why
what thought came before that I thought
of a Christmas tree why I was thinking
of the glowy lights on the tree why
because the sunlight coming into the
window was glowing okay so when you get
really good at meditation when you get I
think it's close to sua I think it's
close to Mastery in in Jan in the path
of preparation
which is a very important state to reach
right I think it's close to that but you
start being able or you start taking an
interest in the chain of thoughts that
brought you here off your object okay so
try that as a I'm I'm giving you a
really important
meditation exercise okay that you won't
find in a book it's that uh when you're
close to seeing
emptiness uh you can trace thoughts back
quite far weeks
months okay it's very interesting okay
so try that maybe it's a kind of semi
Clairvoyance or something but but you
can do it grunt work you know you don't
have to skip to three weeks ago the
thought that brought on this today's
thought you can work back grunt work you
know say okay what was the thought just
a minute before that oh was Christmas
tree what came up just what H what
triggered the Christmas tree Christmas
lights triggered the Christmas lights
the glow of the
sunlight okay and then do that as an
exercise sometimes grab your distraction
and trace it back and it will strengthen
your meditative capacity okay it's a
very powerful tool
okay it's a distraction during
meditation but you can mentally call a
stop to the
meditation yes honestly you can do that
you can say okay I'm done with the room
and I'm now I'm going to trace that
thought back before I get up before I
open my eyes that's
legal as long as it's very conscious
would you use it to get back to the
object you can yeah and then you could
go back to the object can stay on the
object somewhere that's a cool trick
that's one of
those what do you call it elliptical
orbits back to the object rather than
you know tug
all
right okay we were enjoying Nar and
beaut like enjoy the ride is it
considered a distraction if we try to
find more reasons why we're enjoying it
so much to keep it up there yeah it is a
distraction
yeah but I I will say that you can
declare it a progression of the
meditation
that I'm going to progress now into a
state of when you get to tter it would
be a state of bliss you see so I'm
purposely G to crank this up I what I
want you to try to
feel when I'm
saying try to feel a sense of well-being
and contentment that is characterized by
the willingness to stay
there okay so you feel well-being and
you feel contentment and you feel almost
a
joy in the
meditation that inspires you to want to
stay there and so you're surrendering
into the
meditation
uh because the big problem with the big
problem in meditation is that a new
caric seat opens and and and you think
of something else so you have to fight
those right and
you and again I repeat from something
from this afternoon that um or this
morning was it
uh a person who has good n or meditative
contentment to stay in that place with
that object will also be able to stay in
a room quietly for 5 10 20 minutes and
not be hyper you know they they don't
need to get up and do five things and
they're not Dull either okay they're not
like watching TV and they're not
lounging around on the couch they are
sitting straight up in a chair they are
fully aware they are engaged and they're
not doing anything you know they're just
content with the place they be here now
thing right I like that I I wish I had
invented that I mean it sounds really
hippie but it's really true you know
just be here now you and not this
compulsion to do more stuff you know
that a person who has that ability to be
here now without feeling a compul to do
more stuff at the moment and just enjoy
5 minutes it's okay to eat a cookie but
eat it slowly and enjoy it you know uh
and then that's a sign of a good
meditation practice a person who's
meditating well enjoys things
more uh because they take
time because they're not like all the
hyper they got to move on to something
else right away okay that's a sign that
your meditation is pretty
good all right you got to move on to
dinner by the way the way we cond these
things later is uh I'll blah blah I'll
ask you questions and maybe people will
write they'll write down something and H
they'll give it to me and
we'll go like that okay so after dinner
you're going to stop
talking you know in the threeyear
retreat the last year three rat it got
kind of out of hand I won't say who okay
it wasn't me but it was like it was like
this
you know and that was supposed to be
silence you know and then the other
person would
going then theyd
say and then there'd be this for some
reason Whispering it was was okay and
then the GU Michael's problem was that
whistling rock and roll songs was
technically not talking
[Laughter]
okay all right so silence means
silence and you
can you know try to try to keep real
silent try not to what do they call it
tze it or quanze or what gze it there's
these bah rules that you know
technically I didn't break it cuz you
know I sneezing at the same
time when how about we say when you
leave the cafeteria because I I feel
it's fun to bond with people in the
cafeteria dinner will end
at you got to be back here
at
7:45 so uh let's say when you leave the
cafeteria so you know if you're really
desperate to talk you can stay in the
cafeteria till 7:44
yeah I changed
it I forgot what I said